Guide to the Joseph Brodsky papers from the archives of the Katilius family, 1966-1997 M1960
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
Joseph Brodsky papers from the archives of the Katilius family
1966-1997
M1960
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
4.25 Linear feet (8 manuscript boxes and 1 legal half manuscript box)
Documents concerning Russian poet’s Joseph Brodsky’s (1940-1996) personality and his creative work from the family archives of his friends Ramunas Katilius and Elmira Katiliene.
Brodsky, Joseph, 1940-1996
Katiliene, Elmira
Katilius, Ramunas
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased by Stanford University, Special Collections in June, 2013.
History
This collection of Joseph Brodsky papers are from his friends Ramunas Katilius and Elmira Katiliene, who had a close friendship with Brodsky during the years 1966-1970.
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Scope and Contents
The papers contain correspondence with the Katilius family; drafts (manuscript and typescript) of Joseph Brodsky’s poems (circa 70 items / circa 100 pages); a collection of poems compiled and typed by Joseph Brodsky himself (100 pages); Vladimir Maramzin’s samizdat collection (text hand-typed and distributed by hand to avoid censorship) of Joseph Brodsky’s poetry in 3 volumes (circa 900 pages); the poet’s drawings (12 items); and photographs (87 items). Ramunas Katilius and Elmira Katiliene have also collected a wide range of printed materials (including copies) about Joseph Brodsky’s public activities, his interviews for different journals, and articles on Joseph Brodsky’s relations with Lithuania.
The main collection of Joseph Brodsky papers is at Yale, OCLC #702181668. Brodsky papers are also in St. Petersburg at the National Library of Russia.
Abaeva-Myers, Diana; Antanaitis, Algirdas Titus; Baryshnikov, Mikhail, 1948-; Blekaitis, Jurgis; Etkind, Efim, 1918-1999; Golyshev, Viktor; Maramzin, Vladimir, 1934-; Martirosov, Sergei Mushegovich; Misiunas, Audras; Miłosz, Czesław; Myers, Alan; Proffer, Carl R.; Proffer, Ellendea; Rein, Evgenii; Schilz, Veronique; Sozzani-Brodsky, Maria; Stoppard, Tom; Šilbajoris, Rimvydas, 1926-2005; Venclova, Tomas, 1937-; Poets, Russian; Russian poetry.
- Series 1. Biographical file
  - Writings about Brodsky
    - Writings by Ramunas Katilius, 1990-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Writings by Ramunas Katilius, 2000-2008 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Writings by Ramunas Katilius, 1990-1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Various articles concerning Joseph Brodsky, 1988-1997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Various articles concerning Joseph Brodsky, 1997-2002 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Various articles concerning Joseph Brodsky, 2009-2010 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Iliustruotas Kulturos Gyvenimo Zurnalas: Naujoji Romuva, 1997-2003 (Half-box 9, Folder 1)
  - Brodsky and Lithuania
    - Articles on Joseph Brodsky and Lithuania, 1997-2003 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Articles on Joseph Brodsky and Lithuania, 2003-2008 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Articles on Joseph Brodsky and Lithuania, 2008-2011 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Serial on Joseph Brodsky and Lithuania in "Mokslo Lietuva", 2006-2007 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Joseph Brodsky and Lithuanians in United States: Algirdas Titus Antanaitis, Audra Misiunas, Rimvydas Silbajoris, Jurgis Blekaitis, 1991-2007 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Joseph Brodsky and Tomas Venclova, 1998-2006 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Joseph Brodsky and his milieu, 1996-2009 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Ardis Publishers, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Poem Kavine Neringa: Restorano Valgiarastis (Half-box 9, Folder 1)
  - Interviews
    - Joseph Brodsky's account of dealings with Visa and Registration Department, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Joseph Brodsky's interviews, 1976-1996 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Ramunas Katiliu's interviews and speeches about Joseph Brodsky, 1996-2000 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Ramunas Katiliu's interviews and speeches about Joseph Brodsky, 2005-2010 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Public activities
    - Joseph Brodsky's public activities, 1976-1996 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Death and burial
    - Obituaries and writings about the death of the poet, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Memorial service: New York, The Cathedral of St. John the Divine, March 8, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Reburial in Venice, Italy in 1997 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Memorial in Vilnius University, July 8, 1996: Czeslaw Milosz, Yevgeny Rein, Tomas Venclova (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Opening of the Memorial plaque at Liejyklos 1, Vilnius: 2000 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Commemorative events in honour of Joseph Brodsky
    - Scientific conferences, 1991-1995 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Publication of the bilingual collection of Josef Brodsky's poetry: Vilnius, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - International Scientific Conference in Saint Petersburg, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Exhibition at Lithuanian National Library: Vilnius, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - The Joseph Brodsky Museum in Saint Petersburg (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Vilnius Conference, 2010 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Series 2. Correspondence
  - Joseph Brodsky's post-cards and letters to Katilius family, 1971-1974 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Joseph Brodsky's leter to Leonid Brezhnev, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Series 3. Writings
  - Manuscripts
    - Catalogue, by Ramunas Katilius (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Drafts and typescripts of poems, 1962 and 1963 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Unfinished rhymed script for a documentary film: Rembrandt (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Drafts and handwritings of poems, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - The collection of poems: The Stop in the Desert (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Drafts, handwritings and typescripts of poems, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Drafts and typescripts of poems, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Drafts, handwritings and typescripts of poems, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - The Lithuanian Divertissement: handwritings and typescripts, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Poems for BBC broadcast, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Handwritings of English verses (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Early publications
    - Publication in the Tartu University newspaper, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Reprint of an Ardis publication, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - SAMIZDAT papers
    - Vladimir Maramzin's collection of Joseph Brodsky's poetry, authorized by the author before 1972: Part 1 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Vladimir Maramzin's collection of Joseph Brodsky's poetry, authorized by the author before 1972: Part 2 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Vladimir Maramzin's collection of Joseph Brodsky's poetry, authorized by the author before 1972: Part 3 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Vladimir Maramzin's collection, typewtitten by Sonia Rivkind, 1982/83: Part 1 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Vladimir Maramzin's collection, typewtitten by Sonia Rivkind, 1982/83: Part 2 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Vladimir Maramzin's collection, typewtitten by Sonia Rivkind, 1982/83: Part 3 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Samizdat-type papers containing poetry, typed at Joseph Brodsky's request (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Samizdat-type papers containing poetry, typed at Joseph Brodsky's request (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Samizdat-type papers containing various texts, typewritten at Joseph Brodsky's request (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Joseph Brodsky's writings translated into other languages, by others
    - Translation of poems into English, 1975-2000 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Translation of poems into Lithuanian, 1976-2000 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Translation of essays into Lithuanian, 1993-1998 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Series 4. Translations by Joseph Brodsky into Russian
  - Poems of different poets (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Drama by Tom Stoppard: Rosencrantz and Guildenstern are dead, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Series 5. Drawings
  - Drawings with notes and poems (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Series 6. Photographs
  - Till 1963
    - Childhood and youth: donated to Elmira Katiliene by the Mother of Joseph Brodsky after his emigration (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - The time of geological expeditions (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - On the balcony of the Brodsky's apartment, Leningrad, Pestel str., 1963: photo by A. Brodsky, the poet's father. Copy from the archives of M. Milchik (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - The time of geological expeditions (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Norenskaya, Arkhangelsk district
    - Norenskaya, 1964: photo by Ya. A. Gordin. Copy from the archives of M. Milchik (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Life in the North (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Before exile
    - In Leningrad, at home (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - With Yevgenyi Rein, on the balcony of the Brodsky's apartment: photo by A. Brodsky (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - In "the half of the room", Jaunuary, 1968 - March, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Last years in Soviet Union
    - Casting at the Odessa film studio, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Spring of 1972: photo by A. Brodsky. Copy from the archives of M. Milchik (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - With Ramunas Katilius, at the Brodsky's apartment, end of 1971/beginning of 1972: photo by A. Brodsky (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Armenia, end of April, 1972: With friends Sergei i Nelli Martirosov (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Armenia, end of April, 1972: With friends Sergei i Nelli Martirosov, and with Professor Viktor Ambartsumian and his wife (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Ushkovo, Leningrad district: in the summerhouse of Prof. Yefim Etkind, end of May 1972 (according to V. Poluchina, May 21): With Yefim Etkind, Ramunas Katilius, Tomas Venclova, Era Korobova: Photo by Maria Etkind (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Ushkovo, Leningrad district: in the summerhouse of Prof. Yefim Etkind, end of May 1972: With Ramunas Katilius, Maria Etkind (daughter of Prof. Etkind), Tomas Venclova, Era Korobova: Photo by Yefim Etkind (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Ushkovo, Leningrad district: in the summerhouse of Prof. Yefim Etkind, end of May 1972: With Ramunas Katilius and Tomas Venclova: Photo by Maria Etkind (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Ushkovo, Leningrad district: in the summerhouse of Prof. Yefim Etkind, end of May 1972: Ramunas Katilius and Tomas Venclova, Era Korobova: Photo by Maria Etkind (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Departure
    - Photos for emigration documents, May 1972 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - June 4, 1972, early morning: in front of the house on the Pestel str., on the right taxi driver, on the left Ramunas Katilius: photo M. Milchik (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - June 4, 1972, morning: at Pulkovo, in front of the airport: prsemably the last photo in Soviet Union: photo M. Milchik (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Photos from West, beginning from 1972
    - The first Joseph Brodsky's apartment in USA: 1372 Marlborough str., Ann Arbor (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - With Carl and Ellendea Proffer: San Francisco, December 8, 1972: donated to E. and R. Katilius by Ellendea Proffer (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Venice: Christmas, 1974: photo by Veronique Schiltz (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Venice: Christmas, 1975: photo by Diana Abaeva-Myers (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - With Maria Sozzani-Brodsky, his wife: 1991: photo by Diana Abaeva-Myers (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Milan: Christmas, 1974: photo by Veronique Schiltz (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Paris: Summer, 1974: photo by Diana Abaeva-Myers (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - London: Summer, 1976: with Diana and Alan Myers, and Samuel Ramer in Myers' apartment (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - At International Conference on Osip Mandelstam, School of Slavonic and East European Studies, University of London: July 1-5, 1991: photo by Irena Veisaite (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Reburial in Venice, June 1997: photos by Diana Abaeva-Myers
    - The tomb (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Ramunas Katilius and Elmira Katiliene (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Palazzo Moccenigo, after the ceremony of reburial: Maria Sozzani-Brodsky, with her and Joseph's daughter Anna Maria Alexandra, and Mikhail Baryshnikov (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Palazzo Moccenigo, after the ceremony of reburial: Diana Abaeva-Myers with Elmira and Ramunas Katilius (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Palazzo Moccenigo, after the ceremony of reburial: in the foreground Czeslaw Milosz (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Joseph's friends on the eve of reburial: Yevgenij Rein, Elmira Katiliene, Lev and Nina Losev, Nadia Rein, Tomas Venclova, Ramunas Katilius (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Joseph's friends on the eve of reburial (Hotel Buccinttoro): Ramunas Katilius and Elmira Katiliene, Yevgenij Rein, Tomas Venclova, Diana Abaeva-Myers (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Joseph's friends on the eve of reburial: Yevgenij Rein and Tomas Venclova (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Joseph's friends on the eve of reburial: Elmira Katiliene and Ramunas Katilius (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Joseph's friends on the eve of reburial: Elmira Katiliene and Ramunas Katilius and Diana Abaeva-Myers (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Commemorative events
    - Memorial in Vilnius University, July 8, 1996: Czeslaw Milosz and Ramunas Katilus (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Opening of the memorial tablet in Vilnius, Lithuania: October 2, 2000: Wislawa Szymborska, Valdas Adamkus, Czeslaw Milosz, Guenter Grass and Tomas Venclova at the ceremony: photos by Donata Mitaite (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - The memorial tablet on the facade of the house at Liejyklos street (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Guenter Grass, Czeslaw Milosz, Tomas Venclova and Wislawa Szymborska after the ceremony (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Pranas Morkus, Ramunas Katilus, Elmira Katiliene and Audronis Katilius with his wife Violeta after the ceremony (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Friends
    - Viktor Golyshev, his wife Natasha, and their son Vasia (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Carl Proffer with his daughter Arabella (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Group of friends, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Veronique Schilts, Venice: Christmas, 1974: photo by Joseph Brodsky (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Veronique Schilts, Normandie: 1974 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Cotswald, England: 1976: Veronique Schilts, Diana Abaeva-Myers, Alan Myers: (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Romas Katilius, January or February 1972: photo by Joseph Brodsky (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Elia Katiliene ("Khanum"), August 1978 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      Grass, Günter, 1927-; Morkus, Pranas; Szymborska, Wisława
    - Ramunas Katilius and Elmira Katiliene with their sons Andrius (b. 1967) and Ramunas (b. 1971): May 1980 (Box 8, Folder 5)